Oh.
Yeah.
2.
Uh.
OK.
OK, I just put it in a little bit here.
Sorry.
But.
Right.
OK.
Today we start to have some exercise.
So first of all.
OK.
Oh, I shot. So first of all.
The information I already started at the
end of the last class on Thursday,
so exam.
Project and oral exam.
So oral exam will be oral exam. OK,
so you're supposed to have studied the
continuation passing time,
like your closure and.
Dramas, uh,
combines the runtimes and everything.
Uh.
And end up will be basically unusual and
of course.
There will be some.
Maybe first question revolving around.
The the project,
the project I will I will publish
projects after of course this thing.
It's always made with the agreement with
Andrea.
But uh, personally,
I think it would be nice to publish.
Uh, by the end of this week,
a number of potential projects that you
can pick up.
And as I was saying and we will give some
rating of the project,
but honestly I have no idea.
On how to read the the the assignment so.
At least for me in the grade,
but I have to discuss this with them that
the grade will be more a way to give you
a feedback.
Then a way to say, OK, your project is 25,
but you can get more.
You cannot get more than 28. In any case,
basically that is.
The the idea it is an experiment
discourse and so also the project would
be experimental and personally I think
and I was I am the.
The one who came up with this proposal of
project,
I think that this should be for you,
an opportunity to force yourself.
In doing a significant job using the AI
around the notions of the course and by
also having your mind.
Sat on, you know what you're doing.
I mean,
you're not anymore someone that have
basically asked something to GPT just
because you didn't feel yet. OK,
as I was saying, basically.
You are supposed to supposed to submit
three things.
One is I guess a PDF file or in case of a
software project also a zip will be OK so
that we can compile it, but basically.
The output of your use of the AI,
which of course if it's well done,
we will give a super nice grade to the AI,
not to you,
because that that is AI's contribution,
but it is the way to.
Submit the result.
So I guess that that will be your
submission to someone someone else or.
Not letting you to use AI and you try to
use the AI to pass the X.
OK then you have also to produce two
other things.
The prompts, I mean,
I'm not saying that you have to submit
all the trace of all your interactions
with the AI. They will,
there will be prompts with the prompts of
just things and it's pointless to go to
that level also for us to read.
OK, So what are the meaningful prompts,
even bad ends? I mean,
it would be nice to say, OK,
I try to ask this question and the
results were not that interesting.
As I thought they will be,
and so I went that way. OK,
but basically all the problems that we
use to produce the output. Oh, by the way,
the output is not necessarily a single
shot.
It's totally acceptable for programming
that you generate one file at a time for
for a document.
It may be the collation of multiple file
or multiple steps. OK, so the.
It's not an exercise to have one prompt
that gives you the output.
Basically you want to make the eye making
the hard work and you are the supervisor
of the eye and you have to question the
eye.
Ask for you have to improve this.
You need to double check things and the
third ingredient of the submission is how.
You check the output.
Which is, by the way,
the most important thing,
because I'd like to leave as long as I
can leave without having some sort of
approval by someone of you without.
Double checking on my card.
Then I got a cash accident because there
was a bugging. OK,
that's basically the submission.
The idea is you should be able to do it
in a couple of weeks, OK,
not full time you.
You have also other assignments,
other exams, etcetera.
So I think it's unfair to pressure you
more than that.
Since it is an experiment, please,
please play the game with us.
There's no point in cheating.
Have discussions.
They're more than welcome. OK,
exchange opinion among you.
It's OK.
That's not something I I hope you will
take this as an opportunity to grow,
to personally grow in a field where you
you are among the first.
Trying to be certain,
so take the opportunity and there's no
point. At the end of the day,
the final game will be set at the oral
exam and then you should be as prepared
as you can be.
And of course you have to remember things.
But at the end of the day,
the hope about this course is that you
have spent time thinking about concepts,
not features of the language,
because features.
They were important, I mean 10 years ago.
I think.
15 years ago,
one of the last time I did this course,
teachers were important.
Back then, programming was about Googling.
Backward flow and writing code.
So knowing the feature was of paramount
importance to be productive. OK,
nowadays it's still important,
but it's more important that you
understand the.
Hidden structure that I try to align and
there try to align across multiple tasks
in the languages and then I hope you
appreciated all the field rouge that
OK, the.
binds.
Apparently different languages,
and sometimes because the programming
language is a trade-off,
every beat of the programming language
lets you sacrifice some other feature on
the programming language.
And it's a compromise.
So it's not the point. I mean,
there are bad languages, Python, sorry.
But there are no good languages.
I mean there are some languages that are
more applicable than others to represent
some computation and it's OK then the the
novelty is that now you can explore.
Learn and generate code using a tool that
is capable of understanding is fairly
productive in the space of formal
language. The eye is really, really.
Google with formal language is more than
not a manage.
It's a place where you you can get some
satisfaction.
Of course you can also ask not for the
core, you can also ask for.
I don't know if you decide to go and
generate a system that works,
so a program.
Then you may also ask instruction on how
to which is the best way to set up the
project etcetera.
I mean it's not only related to give me
the algorithm function or the file.
You can aim uh at the project.
So someone of you asked about the
projects. OK, again, being an experiment,
we will try to figure out something that
can be done in a couple of weeks,
but at the end of the day.
Uh.
Any output that can be more or less
sophisticated,
so I don't expect that the problems will
be too detailed first.
Because I think that you're and you must
be measured enough the.
To fill out the blanks. OK,
I mean this is not a first year
mathematical analysis course in which you
have to say this this is the function,
give me the limits and there is one.
Good answer in in programming and in
general in the real world there are.
Wrong gangsters.
As many as you want.
Brilliantly the right answer.
And you got a bunch of reasonable answers.
And so in all my projects,
typically I encourage students to take
this approach. I mean,
tell me why you think it's OK as a
solution.
So if you are investigating,
you have to decide where do you stop.
Insertion. OK, I mean,
remember the web assembly.
Where do you stop? Semantics,
implementation, future directions,
different implementation and comparison
across implementations. It's up to you.
OK,
take and use your time to produce the
output that you would like to submit to
your boss,
hopefully in a couple of years from now
when you will be paid for your work.
If it's OK for your boss,
it may be also good for you.
I'm assuming a skilled boss otherwise.
Bye.
So.
There will be a flat piece of progress,
but at some point some of you challenged
me,
asking me for what kind of investigation
will be requested to perform. So I.
Produce a classification,
but it's not mandatory.
I mean it's just there are there will be
3 broader areas of request.
The first one will be generative.
If you're someone that likes to program,
if you like, you can generate a program.
Uh.
If you like to investigate to learn more
about a specific subject.
Then beat. I mean,
let's take a programming language or a
feature of programming language, etcetera,
and do the work of learning all the
internal features.
How they've been used,
how they have affected the the evolution
of other programming languages.
We'll learn during the course that in
general this is the norm.
Programming languages tend to influence
for each other.
So that that's another and the third one
is instead.
Go and read some really cool base and
with the help of AI try to fill the gap
together a reasonable feeling of a
specific feature of a flow base.
We did it. We did it with the CLR.
There are several interesting code bases
that can range from the kernel of Linux.
Uh, the web browser.
These are the obvious. Uh.
The values of React JS framework,
Angular JS, all these frameworks,
all of them are full of these database
implementation, MySQL, Postgres,
DB etcetera.
All of these are interesting codebase
where you may.
Like to uh uh.
To deepen your understanding, OK.
And for this reason apart from the list
that that we will publish so that I mean
we can we help you if you don't have a
particular ideas.
I personally encourage you if you want to
do something along these three lines of
thinking that you like,
because you're already working apart from
studying because you're curious and you
want to learn.
Uh, sound bigger.
Please write to me and Andrea and say OK,
I've seen the list of projects.
I'd like to do this.
And we simply double check that the
project is not too difficult. Yeah,
because those that want to depend the
knowledge,
they are under the risk of working too
much for for the output.
Or it's too dumb to be a project. OK,
so we need to balance things.
But apart from that,
feel free to propose if you think your
favorite project.
And I mean,
I think it's a a better way to spend your
time than work on a synthetic project,
just to check that we learn something. OK,
so personally.
And if you're passionate about,
you may even learn things,
which is a good thing. OK,
so that is basically the we will write
down the set of rules along the project
so that you also get.
Uh.
Previous picture of the rules and the
submission that probably likely will be
by submitting a form. That's it.
I mean so today.
Hey.
Today we we do a first exercise and to
start I'd like to develop an application
from scratch.
UI and to make things interesting.
I think we will use and also compatible
with my laptop because I can't afford to
spend the whole day.
Installing packages and stuff.
I decided that we'll use Windows Forms,
which is a fairly old by now framework
for writing applications.
And we have to.
Create.
I think an arcade game.
By the address.
I think it will be. I'm using a mobile.
So now this is the goal and of course the
first thing that you do is I have to
implement the.
Patrice.
Or I can wait. That's I cannot,
I not cannot like game in C# and win
forms.
Uh.
It is. Oh, I mean that's cheat.
It is my assignment.
I'd like to do a super nice application.
Can you help me?
Always remember when you talk to the AI,
most of it is American.
So use the American way.
That's super cool.
Oh.
In the meantime, let let me open.
Pair me now.
So that.
So as you can see us now, Oh yeah, sorry.
OK, this is. First of all,
I forgot to tell one other ingredient,
the AR model. Personally,
I don't care if you use GPT.
So Gemini,
some model that runs on your laptop.
It's OK of course as part of the
submission,
please tell me because the output if you
use an on-prem model.
Maybe not so nice,
but it's valuable because you spend time
using a smaller model and so it's a nice
result because we are evaluating the
questions, not the answer.
Is the answer depends on the quality of
the model you're using.
So don't feel constrained in using GPT
because I did use GPT during the course.
OK,
use the model that you prefer the most.
If you're curious, there is.
There are also.
Codex CLI.
In that case you will need an API key,
but it's you can run it in a container.
I suggest you to do so because Codex CLI
basically allows you to run.
On your machine, the AI,
but that's the AI would run comments on
your product.
So if you care about your machine,
sandbox it inside the container,
that will be a much better way to operate.
And that's it. OK,
so now I'm doing it with.
Uh,
I'm not using codex because codex will be
in principle able to also to generate.
All the the code project and everything
in a single bunch.
Now I'm in the chat like chat mode way of
doing things which is basically available
both on Prem and off Prem.
If you want to run.
On premise models.
How many of you have on Prem have run on
Prem models on your laptop?
So if you want to start because you're
curious, this is nice.
A good place to start is Olama.
OK, Olama, now comes both the.
With the common line and also a web UI
which is very similar.
This is all llama running on our server
and as you can see it is very similar to
GPT or whatever so.
So if you want you start with the llama,
it's fairly easy and one of the things
that the llama does is to produce and
give models and you can also use any
model from a new face.
These are basically the two ways and if
you look for code.
You have called Lama, called Gemma.
And so and so on.
So if you want to experiment,
you can go also this way. And again,
please tell me I use my laptop with this
and of course I will not seek for super
complicated output because you're using
it.
Your your cycles. OK,
let's see the proposal.
So a clean architecture,
a basic playable game.
Ideas for super nice. OK, sounds good.
O.
They propose the form and the.
We proposed to create the the game form.
Now I expect that you had some classes in
UI's,
but in any case form is the typical name
if you use it to talk about a window in a
in a system so.
That's the objects, the core objects,
the paddle,
the bowl and the brakes where the the
bowl bounce.
That would lost the attempting to
reconnect the it's not so.
Not so good.
So we got the network until now and now
that I need it.
OK, maybe it is just the application.
Retry.
Notice now it will get give me a
completely different approach of course,
no more game form.
It's reasonably similar.
There is the game loop.
OK, so first of all.
What do you think that the game look?
Please.
Doesn't mean when you start generating
part of the generation will be about the
domain of your choice.
If you want to generate a music
generation,
you have to know something about music.
Sound waves,
fast Fourier transform and whatever,
because otherwise you will fail to
understand the.
Uh, the output. OK,
so I mean this is our job at the end of
the day, because even before AI,
what we do as a programmer is we
basically.
Then I feel somehow philosophical.
You take me as a.
So let me share this small talk,
small talk with you. So.
One may argue that computer science is
about some problems.
I mean, at least in programming,
would you implement an exponential
algorithm?
No.
Or some non deterministic something? No.
So at the end of the day we write
programs that generate that are either
polynomial, linear polynomial.
And they'll break, but that, you know,
saying.
So at some point in my life I said OK,
so I think that a discipline in which I
face all these stupid problems.
Of course,
sometimes I was a little bit depressed.
I mean, I was looking to physicists,
differential equation engineers,
find hands. I said OK and and I for each.
Really.
Then I realized that something that.
Made U my mind basically.
Our goal is to take something which is
exponential, which is difficult the world.
Quantum computing,
I mean very complicated problems and our
job is to find a way possibly through
approximation to give a tractable
representation in terms of linear or
polynomials.
OK.
And so our contribution is mostly in the
in passing from the super complicated
work that we are modeling down into the
simpler representation that the machine
can be with.
And in this respect, uh, I said OK.
My discipline is not that bad, OK,
but if you look at the output,
the output is sometimes.
And so why I said this?
Because basically in any problem that you
take up, the first thing you have to.
To to do is to try to understand the
domain,
the application domain when I set up my
journey.
In writing the.
I assume that in this university there
were not that many elections.
Since then,
you know more than few other things and I
did take some number of decision in the
UI implementation that were wrong because
I did study a little bit.
The theory of elections,
but I wasn't aware that we do hundreds of
elections per month in this university,
and so part of the VI should be
redesigned because it's already.
Beyond control,
mostly because I didn't know completely
the domain when I started writing code.
OK,
so whenever when you start reading the
output,
the first thing that you have to do.
Is to be sure that you understand the
proposal that the model is making in
terms of the objects.
So this brings us back to the what is the
game loop.
So I mean withdrawal, yes,
but I mean it's not limited to that.
There is some something that a lot of a
lot of calculating things.
So we take a big group when we.
You can overcome this same calculation
with different data for like for example
the the the player movie the the the same.
That's perfect.
In general, the game goal,
as your colleague just stated,
is to produce a new frame of an unleash
every at least 30 times a set.
OK.
And you have some representation of the
objects of the game, the paddle, the bed,
the ball,
the brick and and those are governed by,
I don't know when the ball.
Goes in the tradition of volcanoid,
the speed is constant.
So I mean it is a very bad implementation
of physics, no?
So typically every computer game ranging
from the super complex 3D down to the
arcade at this inner inner structure,
which depends because I mean the game
evolves for the reasons the frame.
First,
some object that you are displaying
should move according to some simulated
feeling,
so some other rule and that's one and the
2nd is.
User interaction.
So.
And since the game is designed to be
interacted constantly,
typically it is more efficient to pull
the keyboard,
pull the joystick or any input,
check the interaction given the
interaction.
Update the internal model.
Of course only the part of the model that
is affected by user actions,
in this case the paddle.
So if there is a right key,
right arrow key,
you have to update the position and the
speed of the paddle so that it goes right.
And and then once you've updated all the
state of your world,
then you've read the the current frame.
OK, that's the a normal.
Way of organizing a computer game.
There are frameworks.
That implement this,
I ask it to use a general framework,
so I expect the AI will generate some of
these data structures by itself.
OK.
Visual niceness, double buffering.
What it is double buffering?
Sorry, OK.
So is right. So basically.
For the sake of of of speed,
I'm blaming the A I in this moment. OK,
I mean answering.
Of course you can go and ask the A I what
is the double top? OK,
you will get the same answer.
But basically the idea is.
When you.
And the graphics context is called.
It's basically the operation that the UI
gives you.
It's an object that allows you to design
to draw on the on your on your window. OK,
so that's the graphics context.
And if you start drawing,
actually the system will update all the
pixels that you're seeing.
So if you're updating multiple objects,
this is unlikely to be updated.
In instantaneously and so the user will
perceive some flickering in the in the in
the refresh. OK, but.
If you allocate an offscreen bitmap,
so basically a buffer with the same
number of pixels on your screen or all of
your window and.
You start writing into that off screen
buffer that basically generates the new
frame.
In the frame buffer there is the current
frame and then you copy the the this.
Hidden buffer into the buffer and only
the different pixel will be updated.
This generates a much stabler update of
the of the frame.
So then this is the standard technique
studied in.
Graphical programming courses and that's
that's it.
OK.
So.
Now we are getting instructions.
And the output OK.
I pick up a a simple project,
so clearly perhaps a single file will be
OK.
I am using.net core and VS code.
How can I start?
So no,
no graphical user interface to to draw
things. OK.
So now I can say OK, I can read,
especially when you execute the uh.
Code please read the the instruction
before copy paste in your shell.
So I know that that is correct, so I.
Paste and I have my.
Roject created.
This generates these files.
OK, this is uh.
Now I can check whether I can run.net run.
And the system in net compiles and run
the application.
So now this is my Windows form graphical
application up and running.
Of course, emty form.
OK now.
We.
Start Visual Studio Code.
I trust the authors, yes.
And as you can see,
it's complicated because you start
trusting this thing even too much because
all the instructions are correct so far.
So first of all.
Let's rename form one. No, sorry.
For one in two.
Rename game form.
Rename.
Game.
Too much.
Game for.
OK.
Now.
We have to rename.
Also the classes because this is these
are the files in C#.
It's not like Java that you are forced to
use this.
The name of the file should correspond to
the class name.
So in principle it will run.
So now I have to update this so game form.
OK.
I also have to change this.
Or constructor.
Of course I can use a some support from.
The the editor to do the so-called code
refactoring.
Code refactoring allows you to rename all
the things because editors this is for
sure for the multi-factor.
Um.
The the code the the editor.
We didn't discuss much this,
but the editor is basically the half of a
compiler.
I mean it has most of the parser.
Of the of the language so that the editor
is able to collapse blocks and see the
code as the abstract syntax tree.
So operations such as rename this class
can be performed by the editor in a
semantic way,
not just search replace linearly.
OK.
Now it's fairly common.
And of course we have to change the
program where we start.
The OK, this is for having a nice code.
From time to time you restart and then.
We get in the designer.
In line 14, sorry.
Thank you.
OK, that was a good.
Right now.
We get these.
So the designer should be replaced with
this.
Now notice that uh.
Notice. Now let me do the dumb user.
So I'm just acting as the servant of the
AI. AI tells me copy here,
do that and I'm doing it. OK,
of course this is the risk.
You're taking and with applications it to
some extent it's easier because at the
end of the day you know that you will run
the application.
So if it's an archonoid game, OK,
if it's not bad, OK, so it's not terrible,
but in general as you.
You can see it's really,
really easy to fall in the trap that you
start following the eye without losing
your brain and contribute to the project.
So let me take this attitude, OK?
Now.
Here I did get.
I so create a new file game objects.
I can make it game objects dot CS.
So as you can see,
the AI tends to generate coding files
because she expects that you will copy,
paste and create the files so that.
O This is the game form.
So.
I forgot something, no?
OK, if we are lucky.
We should be able to run.
OK, so first error.
Time in.
Is ambiguous. Which one would you pick?
Timer is a reference ambiguous between
seats and windows forms timer and system
threading timer. What you would do?
OK, so let's do the down the programmer.
It's complicated. I know the answer. OK,
so I screenshot.
And I guess this is the ever.
I get I created uh and copied the.
Code.
Notice that at least for GPT,
any task that involves programming
typically triggers the thinking model.
Thinking model.
So the comparison to time classes.
For Windows Form game you want system
Windows Forms time.
It was fairly obvious but nevertheless.
It is this way, so game four line 10.
System Windows forms type.
Hmm.
Oh, another one.
59.
Same error now OK being dumb but.
Oh.
OK, sees them in those forms.
So imagine that a bunch of colleagues of
yours spent weeks in implementing these
to pass the exam when I use it to give
the programming interface course.
For so many years,
I mean that was an exercise actually in
15 minutes we we got.
An implementation that would have granted
the pass to a student.
OK now.
Why?
Um, no.
So it oh bug. No, I've got a bug.
I was pressing it,
so the first thing I will probably do is.
OK, no up to you now that we got this.
OK,
so every time you you you you you break a
brick, you have to increment the speed,
OK.
Now.
OK, can you make the physics of the ball?
More realistic.
When?
So actually your colleagues is suggesting
that in a real world you have a bowl and
the paddle is moving,
you have friction that introduce rotation
and in fact they were in Archanoid,
in the original Archanoid they were.
Real approximation typically at the
border.
Actually those have been implemented.
It's in if you have noticed when I the
angle.
The angle at which the.
The ball goes back if I use it,
if I hit using the is changing.
So there is some implementation,
but I think you're right,
it may be interesting to have a more
physical implementation, OK.
Let's do that.
Can you make the physics of the ball more
realistic when you when the ball
interacts with the paddle?
Fiction.
Add the speed.
Ball speed.
Born nurse.
Et cetera.
Two examples.
So now.
If you look at the reasoning, uh,
reasoning, it's interesting.
So I have to change the bounce from
paddle.
I will add these variables,
so reading the output,
especially on thinking mode,
it's really useful for understanding
what's going on. OK, so please do it.
OK.
Now.
What should I update?
So the system generated just the class
paddle.
So now I have to understand the code a
little bit.
So now in this simple uh uh case uh.
We know that there is the.
Game objects.
The paddle should be updated,
so basically I replace the class.
And in game form dot game loop.
In the game form game loop.
We have to add this because we got the
the difference.
I will say this.
I guess only the first because the other
two lines are already there.
So do you think it's a good idea to ask
to regenerate the full?
The full method.
Instead of me making a repeat,
updating all the differences.
So in general, AI is terrible at copying.
Uh, the output.
OK, so if you ask the AI to copy,
typically you get a completely different
result.
This is a problem because if you are
writing code,
I mean it's complicated to restart over
and over because.
Sometimes you may get another
implementation which is different.
And fix some problem,
but introduce new problems that you have.
And so the risk is that you never
converge into a final result.
Of course,
one of the contribution that the Codex
brings to the table is exactly this.
It basically generates the diff with
respect to the current project.
OK,
so this is bounce from paddle when you do.
When you do things like this,
basically with an editor like VS Code,
it's easy.
You collapse the object and then you
replace with a new implementation and.
And then, uh,
if you're a maniac of the code, you also.
Control KF where you format this section.
OK.
If you wanna air friction,
let's have also air friction.
Move into the ball class. Notice that the.
This is in the class no oh.
Oh.
In class bowl, there should be move.
There we are and we replace.
And.
Contra KF.
There we are.
OK, let's see if it works.
Some effect is visible,
so I will say that nice good AI.
OK, next one you were suggesting.
Is the.
Actually the the the game.
Please every brick it gets it bounce into.
Hmm.
Oh, bug.
And and oh, that that that will be OK.
So you see what I was, um.
What?
What was my my point about how deep you
you can go?
I mean this project can be implement an
Arcanoid game like a game in.
In Windows Pharmacy Sharp,
OK and then we did the core job in 10
minutes and now we can go in graphics.
You can go on and on forever.
I mean graphics is never.
Never ever finished.
But I mean is now the problem is we have
to fix bugs. So oh, come on.
Um.
When the bowl hits.
In some places.
Probably at the crossing.
It pops a break without the.
Um, changing.
The reaction this.
Is a bug. Can you fix it?
It's interesting because as you see when
you start changing things,
question gets more complicated and you
have to double check the output.
More thoroughly.
So now.
That bug makes sense.
So let's add two fields to the ball class.
I hope that you start appreciating.
Off.
Class.
How at some point you start feeling the
need to understand the the generated code,
because by copy pasting the risk is that
eventually you will fail.
To understand what's going on.
So for instance, now.
It is changing the.
Uh, the the move implementation,
but it's losing the air friction.
Which I like it,
so I decide to not copy paste the full
method,
but I include only the interesting part.
The bouncer from brick. Oh, by the way,
if you decide to go this way,
it's a good idea to commit into a local
git that you create for the occasion your
code so that you can roll back and.
Uh, so bathroom week is in.
Yeah.
Notice very simple bounds.
She was aware that was very simple bound.
Now it's more complicated.
OK.
Only bounce on one brick per frame,
so basically.
The I found that initial implementation.
You had two months,
two months to set up the MFA two months.
Now you wait O.
The risk is that there are situation in
which you hit with multiple bricks and in
fact the both is that we didn't cross
check,
but I think it it is right is that and
it's a typical the boundary checking in
in games is always a big thing.
Because if you update the position of the
object before changing it,
the risk is that you enter inside an
object, you fail to detect the collision,
and so you may have some transparency
effects inside the game.
So that's that's basically what's
happening.
Um.
OK.
So.
In the game loop, so in the form.
In the game loop, we're already here.
Basically.
The patch allows only one collision for
frame.
5.
And.
The the actually the the the the idea
that the AI does and actually I'm playing
this game uh but I think it it can make
uh sense.
Who? Hallucination.
That is not evident, but basically.
You have a an empty variable.
Unnecessary. OK, no, that was.
The variable is assigned,
but its value is never used. Uh, OK.
Hmm.
She's right,
so let me go back to the previous
implementation.
Actually.
There is the break. Oh, OK,
so basically the the the news is uh,
it generates a uh.
An empty, a useless variable,
but basically the idea is you break from
the loop.
So probably we can remove this,
remove that and still make sense.
This is because, I mean,
we're doing things together with AI,
so don't pretend that everything is
perfect.
OK.
Don't looks to me that it's been fixed.
I don't know.
Let me start again because I have to
check.
This part is correct.
The mounts in that way is OK is OK.
I'm still trying to understand whether
because.
Thank.
And that was the the attempt to.
OK, so I I hope you got the idea of the.
Uh.
So let let's uh uh because uh.
If I was doing a project then that will
be.
Now the game will be interesting because
I have to convince the A I to have me
produce the right output by explaining a
non-trivial behaviour.
I think at some point I would have tried
to record the screen video.
And try to pass the AI in the video.
So look at this. Do you think it's OK?
But let's try that. That's interesting.
So.
You know that in Windows now you you can
if you hit the windows key capital S you
can capture.
And let me start caturing this.
Let me start the thing run.
Oh.
Let me see if I'm able to.
OK.
Let's stop the video.
Unavailable. I I got the game over, OK?
So.
Where is this file now?
Save.
OK.
I'll go.
I join you for the F file download.
You see that at the beginning.
Beginning oh.
The behavior is weird.
This is my first time.
I never tried uh uh to to feed the.
A video.
Oh,
now she pretends that she's understanding.
O Let's change the constructor to this,
OK.
Call.
Uh, the constructor of both.
OK.
OK, boy.
New OK, so reset bull and paddle.
In game 4.
So K4.
Reset.
This this is it. Go there the new.
We have to set up.
OK.
OK,
so let me check that I did save
everything.
That's cool.
This is war.
So if you think that I just provided the
video saying can you fix this,
that's impressive.
I didn't expect this, OK?
OK, let's do a final thing,
which is increase the speed.
Can you now increase the speed as the
user pops bricks?
OK, so while I get the these few lines,
I hope you got the idea on how to produce
this thing so.
Few considerations.
Prompts here are fairly easy to to
comment. OK,
so let's in your board class add this.
OK, so we have to add the.
In the bool class add the these advers.
Terrible. I need the terrible thing.
It's late.
No.
OK.
There we are.
Control KF OK, did it and now.
In bounce.
In bounce from paddle.
This one.
So here the bounce from paddle.
Just replace the keep speed within bounce
pads.
Hmm.
These two at the end, I will say.
OK,
don't ask me why this thing is doing like
this, but nevertheless, OK, which one?
It's, uh, oh, yes.
Thank you.
OK.
O.
You see that the ball is moving like.
Not really constant speed.
It looks like for a small amount of time,
uh is uh speeding up and then uh slows
down.
Why do you think is this?
I cannot generate,
but it takes time to generate plays and
slow down the game, so we should separate.
So your colleague says OK,
the problem is that the code that is
being generated assumes that it is called
every.
6 milliseconds. OK,
but unfortunately the UI system is not so
precise. OK,
so a better way will be to measure to use
time.
To measure the actual speed,
the actual position and compute every
frame you take the current time,
you take the difference with with respect
to the previous frame and then you
compute the physics using the delta T not
with the assuming that the delta T is the.
Milliseconds of the frame. OK,
that will get a much better,
but I think it's fairly nice that in 3/4
of an hour we've been able to generate a
reasonable application from scratch using
Windows Forms not knowing.
Now if this was a project,
you may ask what?
Does it mean to verify? Double check. OK,
so in some of the projects software is it
depends on the software because this this
software was about.
Deleting all the files from your file
system that starts with F and have on the
4th letter A the file,
then the self evidence in running the
application. I won't go that way.
This is a UI application.
If it doesn't work,
we simply kill and restart it and it is
to some extent self applicant.
OK and as a matter of fact I would have
written in the relation.
I did the the checks over time.
For instance,
I had to upload the video so we get
because at some point they don't when you
are application was behaving in the wrong
way.
And and then I first tried with this
prompt to explain to the model which was
but I failed to to get the fix and then I
reported a brief video and I uploaded the
video and asked it for a patch and and
the model would do how to produce it in
and work it etcetera.
OK so the the checks.
Depends on if you're generating text
about some properties of monadic
computation in our scale,
then you have to double check the final.
When you're doing with the code,
the check is part of the development
cycle because you get.
Check.
You have to check because I I hope you
did appreciate that at some point.
The the the code of the bounce from
paddle that it generated,
it was different than the one because in
the context now the model has the simpler
bounce from paddle.
That original generated.
Then I I asked him to make it more
physically possible and he complicated it,
but he forgot about that part and he
generated the simpler version. Again,
I spotted the difference. OK,
I'll do it by myself.
There are several techniques to work
around this.
You can start a new chat and say OK,
I have this application.
You upload the files of the application
and start again from there.
That's acceptable.
Or you start looking and making a
difference and read the code.
Another thing that I would like to see in
the verification is whether the code is
convincing. I mean,
do you think that are there?
Potential condition in which the code the
generated code misbehaves.
Are you sure that the output is always
sound or you did three tests and those
three tests were OK and that's it and you
hope for the best? OK,
so even though the liquidation part in
the software, it may be partly.
Done just by executing.
This doesn't mean that you don't go.
You don't have to go.
You have to go inside,
try to understand the code and try to see
whether the code is behaving as expected.
And I mean the game loop is this correct?
So let's let's have a look at the game
loop.
There are warnings.
These warnings are OK or we should we so
the game loop.
One may argue about this because the game
loop is a call back on the tick of the
timer.
OK,
which is OK in fact because this is a
Windows form application.
That was my requirement.
There are frameworks that allows you to
not have the the.
You can do it also in in Windows forms.
You you you can avoid to process the
event loop and and so you can have a much
more efficient cycle in in the processing.
So I mean you may possibly using another
AI.
Asking whether these implementations are
OK or not. So let's try this.
Cloth.
I have the following implementation of
another canoid game in C# and Winforms.
Forms.
Is the game.
Loop correct.
OK.
And we'll see.
This is a fairly frequent way using
another A I to cross-check the output of
an A I.
Uh.
And actually I expect that.
Mostly correct was good.
UI thread blocking. OK,
this is the fine the end of the game.
In general,
it's not a good idea to use a pop-up.
It's OK.
Uh.
Huh.
OK, reasonable for this. OK,
basically she said. OK, I will do this.
I mean, I I disagree with this,
but I mean this is not the UI programming
course, so.
It's OK. OK,
so I hope to give you an example of how
software development may feel.
Of course these boons scale up to the
full 300 files application.
I mean this works for.
Small applications,
then you need to start using a different
system and the models are the same,
but clearly the codex is capable of
processing the full code base without you
having to code the copy paste, etcetera,
etcetera.
Small application, I mean if you think,
I think this will cover probably 80 or 90
percent,
90% of the Google Play Store and Apple
Store sort of apps, I mean.
No.
No, I mean I'm open. Why not? No,
no the the the kind of applications that
you you manage by this most of the
application you find in the in the store
are basically.
Web application or simple applications
that can be generated this way.
That was my my point.
I mean there are sophisticated
application that you can find in the in
the in in the app,
but I mean if I look at the average
average includes all the stupid games and
all etcetera I think.
That in percentage,
probably 80% can be generated using these
kind of techniques. Beyond that,
I won't say so.
You can.
I think that you can reach the production
grade. I mean, I agree with you that it's,
I mean, it's not a one shot process,
but if you keep going,
you can complicate things as much as you
want.
My personal experience is when you start.
Including graphics,
then things get complicated.
I mean the images are sets so that you
get, you know,
the bricks are with a nice button.
There you can get complication.
Oh, that that part.
It's up to you to describe all these
things,
but if you're good in describing things,
you can get a reasonably result.
But again,
if you're pretending that I need an
application that does this on iOS,
it won't work. Yes, I agree. I mean,
this is something that can help you.
Now the the other question is,
should I use?
Pilot inside Visual Studio which is an
alternative where I can say OK I take
this and I asked to rewrite code.
So should I go for a developer first
approach in which I added the code and AI
helps me writing or should I go into the
generate only?
Way of I need an application and then
keeps going.
I mean that's an open question.
When I started this journey,
I thought it was Visual Studio Code first
and then AI.
When I started writing codex application,
so I mean with a full-fledged model,
then I started saying yes or no.
I mean I can see at least a bunch of
application that you can get
out-of-the-box without need of an edge.
I mean you can then after fix.
The generated code,
but most of the code can be fully
generated. So that's my current feeling.
Nevertheless,
this is part of the exercise,
I mean to learn how to do this.
That.
Trying to use this model,
I try to find a little like.
I'm sorry, hold on.
Sense of me writing.
You have no sense in writing.
I mean you are.
Yeah.
Like the chief of like how is still my
ship if I change every single bit.
It's a different rule.
The rule becomes that you are the
guardian.
That ensures that this thing is safe for
people to use,
and it's much more difficult because I
tell you,
it's much easier to write code than read
code. Read code is much more difficult,
really more.
This is one of the reason because I
shifted the course this year,
because you need to understand much more
things to be able to read code than write
code. OK,
so if you if you think that you're losing.
Your role? No, you're not.
You're getting a much more sensible role.
And I said when we started this course,
if you remember, I told you, look,
it will be, or at least it seems,
and I may be wrong,
that the word is coming.
There will be much less.
Job place and posts for programmers
because and those will be for ********
highly skilled programmers because web
programmers are dying.
It's just a matter of cycles.
The last announcement of GPT-5 they shown
that that they improved the also the nice
design of the code generated from the
from GPT and they.
Failing the model to to do better designs.
OK,
so it's just a matter of cycles of of
training and I'm pretty sure a full web
application will be generated and it's
and my feeling is I'm doing artifacts
with clothes since the beginning the
latest.
Versions are full-fledged application.
If I show you the original artifacts,
they were shaky, not so good, etc.
But the latest one are basically micro's
application ready to go,
even if you ask for a dashboard.
You've got a very nice dashboard. OK,
now you have to play some editor,
whether it's Power BI or some other
application to do all these things.
And then you say this is the data.
Can you generate the dashboard?
And I got an interactive dashboard with
all the pipes and then.
Stuff and write these things.
So it's just the beginning.
GitHub released Spark.
Spark is basically the idea that on when
you're in the go you can write and
develop micro applications.
So the state of what we are today is a
micro application can be generated.
OK,
but if you start thinking along this way,
you may think, OK,
I write the spec office of my application,
I write all the back office APIs,
the data model exam and then I start
generating micro application.
Then use the background API.
I said I'll save a lot of time because
most of the time typically is UI
development and and then I focus in
developing and maintaining the core
business logic with all the APIs and
everything.
So it's an open question.
I have no answer,
but this is happening now. Uh, cursor.
You you know cursor.
How many person? OK,
the rest go and check is getting a fairly
popular AI environment.
It was on stage with open AI because they
use open AI and they announced a few
months ago that they generate or not by
now 40% of the vote.
Or less. OK, so I mean, but again,
the important part is what you did.
These are the fiction.
Go and check that that is the fiction.
Go and check that the output is as the
quality that it needs.
And to do the verification,
you must be a very good programmer,
perhaps even a better programmer.
Than the than the one that runs the code.
OK,
so be sure that your you see that one
rule and it's a more delicate,
especially when this code will run on a
device, on a car, on an airport.
Because at some point it will be the code
generated. So,
so far it's just about convenience.
You know that the fastest quick sort
implementation worldwide has been
generated by Alphagodo.
OK, if you try to read the algorithms,
it's almost uncomprehensible.
So don't think that the AI will simply
generate the code that you will write.
As the models and the machine grows,
it will generate code that you will never
think of writing and you will find too
complicated.
And as long as this process will go on.
They will.
We will need to develop techniques to
double check that that thing really
satisfy my requirements. Oh,
that's an open question.
That's an open question. I mean,
I have no answer to that. It's true,
but actually we roll dice.
And the dice basically,
you know that without rolling dice,
other than some basically useless.
So apparently rolling the dice by the
alias introduced changes which made the
these models.
Show me again.
Unexpected behaviors.
So in principle you can expect you can
get unexpected both. OK, sorry, it's late.
Thank you. See you on Wednesday.
See.